<!--
  Copyright 2006 Webmedia Group Ltd.
 
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<preface id="intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
      Aranea is a <emphasis>Java Hierarchical Model-View-Controller Web Framework</emphasis> that provides a common simple approach to building the web application components, reusing custom or general GUI logic and extending the framework. The framework is assembled from a number of independent modules with well-defined responsibilities and thus can be easily reconfigured to perform new and unexpected tasks. The controller is separated into a hierarchy of components that can react to user or system events. The framework is completely view agnostic, but provides a thorough library of JSP custom tags that target building GUIs without writing a line of HTML. All components and modules are simple <emphasis>Plain Old Java</emphasis> classes without any XML mappings and thus usual Object-Oriented design techniques can be applied. Aranea manages the component field persistence automatically and inherently supports nested state.
    </para>      

    <para>
      Aranea is logically separated in the following modules:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Aranea Core</term> 
          <listitem>Contains the core interfaces and base implementations that define Aranea base abstractions and their contracts. Includes packages <literal>org.araneaframework</literal> and <literal>org.araneaframework.core</literal> and is packaged into <literal>aranea-core.jar</literal> .JAR file.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Aranea Framework</term>
          <listitem>Framework module sits on top of the <emphasis>Core</emphasis> module and contains the implementation of the Aranea Web Framework that does not directly depend on any container. <emphasis>Framework</emphasis> module includes package <literal>org.araneaframework.framework</literal> and its subpackages and is packaged into <literal>aranea-framework.jar</literal> .JAR file.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Aranea Servlet</term>
          <listitem>Servlet module extends the <emphasis>Framework</emphasis> module with services that use a Servlet container. Servlet  module includes package <literal>org.araneaframework.http</literal> and its subpackages and is packaged into <literal>aranea-servlet.jar</literal> .JAR file.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Aranea Spring</term>
          <listitem>Spring module integrates Aranea with the <emphasis>Spring</emphasis> IoC container. Spring module includes package <literal>org.araneaframework.integration.spring</literal> and its subpackages and is packaged into <literal>aranea-spring.jar</literal> .JAR file.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Aranea UiLib</term>
          <listitem>UiLib module contains reusable GUI widgets and supporting API. UiLib module includes package <literal>org.araneaframework.uilib</literal> and its subpackages and is packaged into <literal>aranea-uilib.jar</literal> .JAR file.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Aranea JSP</term>
          <listitem>JSP module contains a custom tag library, including tags that render <emphasis>UiLib</emphasis> widgets. JSP module includes package <literal>org.araneaframework.jsp</literal> and its subpackages and is packaged into <literal>aranea-jsp.jar</literal> .JAR file.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Aranea Backend</term>
          <listitem>Backend module contains supporting classes that are to be used in the application service layer (e.g. backend list data provider helper classes). Backend module includes package <literal>org.araneaframework.backend</literal> and its subpackages and is packaged into <literal>aranea-backend.jar</literal> .JAR file.</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Usage Scenarios</title>

    TODO
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Organization</title>

    TODO
  </sect1>
  
</preface>
